A Guide to the Papers of the Randolph Family of Edgehill and Wilson Cary Nicholas,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Randolph Papers
  - 1838 January 5 Robert C. Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Nicholas states that he is engaged in a "very unprofitable and tedious discussion on abolition" with General Smith as per Calhoun's Resolutions. He is waiting to hear from Randolph on some issues before he goes before the committee, especially the currency issue, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:70)
  - 1838 January 23 Patsey Taylor to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Various domestic matters such as health, education and leisure activities, including reading Napoleon's biography and other books, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:71)
  - 1838 February 20 Robert C. Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Discusses [Henry] Clay's Sub-treasury Bill, which he characterizes as an "infernal bill" which will be pushed to a decision in the Senate while still in an unacceptable shape, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:72)
  - 1838 March 6 Robert C. Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Finds Randolph's reasons for supporting the Sub-treasury Bill fallacious and discusses the charge that "anti-sub-treasuryists" are the vassals of the banks; he encloses a copy of a bill lately passed by the Legislature of Louisiana to regulate and restrict their banks for his edification, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:73)
  - 1838 June 27 Robert C. Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Writes that the Sub-treasury Bill was lost, and asks that Randolph send to Mr. Buchanan the "Rules and Regulations of the University" that Randolph gave him previously but was mistakenly left behind in their room, 1 page (Box-folder 5:74)
  - 1838 September 1 Robert C. Nicholas to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Having left the Guyandotte [River] on Tuesday morning, he mentions the ills of traveling to New Orleans when the river is low and various items, 1 page (Box-folder 5:75)
  - 1834 March 8 Thomas Shores to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Shores has decided to bring his agency in the Jefferson Lottery to a close, eleven tickets are still out and he ask Randolph to draw upon him for the amount of $110.00, 1 page (Box-folder 5:76)
  - 1840 June 24 Patsey Taylor to Jane Randolph. Concerns the safety of her sister and other matters of friends and family, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:77)
  - 1840 August 10 Bernard Peyton to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Business matters concerning two notes, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:78)
  - 1840 September 8 Thomas C. Randolph to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Asks what he should do with the works of Jefferson still on hand in Vickburg, 1 page (Box-folder 5:79)
  - 1841 January 13 Patsey Taylor to Mrs. Francis G. Ruffin, [Caryanne?]. Domestic matters and sends best wishes to Caryanne in light of her recent marriage, asking her to visit before their mother leaves, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:80)
  - 1841 April 26 John Thompson Jr. to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Business matters concerning his draft, 1 page (Box-folder 5:81)
  - 1841 June 30 Patsey Taylor to her mother, Mrs. Thomas Jefferson Randolph, [Jane], An account of her travel to Leesburg and other matters of family and friends, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:82)
  - 1841 July 30 John R. Triplett to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Business matters, 1 page (Box-folder 5:83)
  - 1841 August 10 Dr. H[enry] I[ngersoll] Bowditch to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Requests either the originals or copies of the correspondence of his father, Nathaniel Bowditch, to Thomas Jefferson, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:84)
  - 1841 August 18 Thomas J. Michie to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Expresses the wish to enroll his daughter at Mrs. Randolph's school [the Edgehill School] and asks him for all the pertinent information, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:85)
  - 1841 August 31 Henry Page to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Informs Randolph that his daughter Martha will return to the [Edgehill School] in the Fall, 1 page (Box-folder 5:86)
  - 1841 September 5 Womble and Deane to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns the news upon the arrival of Britannia about the good price of flour, 1 page (Box-folder 5:87)
  - 1841 September 6 [R.W. Gwathmey?] to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Writes concerning a letter from Messrs. Lewis Rogers & Co. of Havre about a sight draft, requesting payment so it can be sent to Mr. Rogers, currently in New York, 1 page (Box-folder 5:88)
  - 1841 September 8 Chapman Johnson to Thomas Jefferson Randolph - with copies of letters from J.J. Sylvester of University College, London, to Johnson and Johnson to Sylvester. Concerns Sylvester's appointment to the professorship of mathematics at the University of Virginia, 3 pages (Box-folder 5:89)
  - 1841 November 11 Womble and Deane to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns a note at [the Farmer's Bank of Virginia?] that cannot be renewed without Colonel Curry's endorsement, 1 page (Box-folder 5:90)
  - 1841 [November] 14 C.D. Everett to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns dental services and other financial matters, 1 page (Box-folder 5:91)
  - 1841 November 29 A.M. Harrison to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Requests on the behalf of a colleague that Randolph use his influence in promoting his election, 3 pages (Box-folder 5:92)
  - 1841 December 10 Stephen Bowers to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Requests the admittance of his sister-in-law, Sally C. Board, as a pupil, 1 page (Box-folder 5:93)
  - 1841 December 27 W. B. Buchanan to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Lengthy letter requesting Randolph's aid in procuring slaves of a specific quality, specifying an elderly couple and a younger daughter, 4 pages (Box-folder 5:94)
  - 1842 January 5 Edward G. Caruthers to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns a misunderstanding concerning a slave named James and whether he was to stay in the service of Caruthers for a year or return to Randolph, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:95)
  - 1842 January 10 Bernard Peyton to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns the value of slaves, which has reduced a third within a month, and his business with Mr. Rogers, 1 page (Box-folder 5:96)
  - 1842 January 12 Womble and Deane to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. A note for $250.00, endorsed by Colonel Carr for P. Trist, must be thrown out for want of a blank, 1 page (Box-folder 5:97)
  - 1842 January 14 W.M. Smith to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Among financial matters, states that the country will have to fight England on the ocean in order to reach her vessels and protect our own shores from desolation, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:98)
  - 1842 January 21 Thomas W. Gilmer to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, concerning a pension for Mrs. Via, discusses the Treasury note bill checkmated by Rives and others in the Senate, and his relationship with Webster is not good enough to approach him on the subject, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:99)
  - [1848] January 31 R[ichard] K[idder] Meade to Mrs. Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Concerns the morality of dancing and other domestic matters, chiefly as a critical response to some issues contained in a previous letter, 4 pages (Box-folder 5:100)
  - 1862 - 1865 G.W. Randolph to his wife, Mary [Elizabeth Adams] Randolph. Four letters and several news clippings concerning George W. Randolph's service to the Confederacy during the Civil War, 16 pages (Box-folder 5:101)
  - 1864 - 1869 Papers of the [Confederate] Soldiers' Christian Association, 21 items (Box-folder 5:102)
  - [1887] April 23 Sarah Nicholas Randolph to W.P. Garrison, sends her apologies for the condition of the manuscript she mailed yesterday, explaining "that the writer is a delicate woman, who being the head of a school numbering over a hundred pupils - thirty-five of whom live in the house with her leads a laborious life and one encompassed with many cares and not a few sorrows." The letter includes twelve pages of extracts from Jefferson Correspondence. (Box-folder 5:103)
  - n.d. Paper sent by unidentified writer to Albert G. Ruffin, concerning whether out of the debt of gratitude to General Andrew Jackson, he should be elected president, comparing him to Sergeant William Jaspers who replaced the flag staff on the battery of Fort Moultrie, Charleston, in the face of heavy British fire, 1 page (draft) (Box-folder 5:104)
  - n.d. Untitled - Ghost Story, 8 pages (Box-folder 5:105)
  - n.d. William Starke to Albert G. Ruffin. Alludes to various matters and subjects, including the trial of some Negroes for hog-stealing, 1 page (Box-folder 5:106)
  - n.d. W.C. Nicholas' instructions to Thomas Jefferson Randolph in bargaining for Pantops. [fragment]. (Box-folder 5:107)
  - n.d. Doctor Nelson's Prescription. Root of Wild Horehound, Root of Black Briar, and Apple Brandy, 2 pages (Box-folder 5:108)
  - n.y. January 15 William Pollard to Albert G. Ruffin. Decline to a dinner invitation, news of Madison and Monroe being put on the electoral ticket, 1 page (Box-folder 5:109)
  - n.y. February 14 Joseph Coolidge to Thomas Jefferson Randolph. Business matters with Messrs. Gray and Bowen, followed by family matters, 1 page (Box-folder 5:110)
  - n.d. J.C.R. [Aunt Jane] to Jane Randolph. Various notes on domestic issues, gardening, chickens, family news, etc., 8 pages (Box-folder 5:111)
  - n.d. Thomas Ritchie to Albert G. Ruffin. Announces the birth of a daughter and other matters, 1 page (Box-folder 5:112)
    Miscellaneous & Financial and Legal
    - 1777 August 6 Map Showing A. Bryans Plan "For Dividing the County of Albemarle and Parish of St. Anne…" [into two parishes?] Perhaps owned by Thomas Jefferson (Box-folder 6:1)
    - 1789 March 2 List of Clothing (Washing) (Box-folder 6:2)
    - 1789 July 20 Receipt - For Money Paid Randolph Jefferson by Nicholas Lewis (Box-folder 6:3)
    - Post 1798 Statement owed Wilson Cary Nicholas by the Heirs of Benjamin Bache (Box-folder 6:4)
    - 1799 October 10 Court Order Signed by Peter Tinsley (Box-folder 6:5)
    - 1799 November News clipping from the Virginia [Argus?]. Half of the front page (Box-folder 6:6)
    - 1810 June 25 Hand-Painted Woodcut of Adair Near Limerick (Box-folder 6:7)
    - [c. 1811 December] News clipping with a Cure for Sores and Information about the 8 th Regiment of Virginia Militia (Box-folder 6:8)
    - 1814 November 11 Unsigned Promissory Note by [Jefferson?] to Patrick Gibson (Box-folder 6:9)
    - 1820 December 1 "Reducing the Interest of Money in this province of Georgia" Certified copy of the earlier law, March 27, 1759, was signed by Secretary of State Abner Hammond and Governor John Clark in 1820 (Box-folder 6:10)
    - 1821 March 7 Albemarle County Court Decision Sent to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, in the lawsuit of the President, Directors, & Co. of the Bank of the United States against Robert C. Nicholas, Wilson C. Nicholas and Thomas Jefferson Randolph, administrators of Wilson Cary Nicholas, deceased (Box-folder 6:11)
    - [ca. 1821] List of Slaves, their Ages and Prices, mentioning Perkins, probably related to the evaluation of slaves in Folder 62 in Box 3, giving a comparison evaluation with another person, represented by initials only (Box-folder 6:12)
    - 1822 January 8 Albert G. Ruffin Admitted to Practice Law in the District Court of the United States for the Alabama District (Box-folder 6:13)
    - 1823 March 6 Promissory Note Signed by Robert Wilson (Box-folder 6:14)
    - 1823 March 8 Promissory Note Signed by John Duncan [?] (Box-folder 6:15)
    - 1823 - 1825 Invoice - For Goods Bought by Miss Eliza Roane from Hall Neilson (Box-folder 6:16)
    - 1824 Jan-Dec Invoice - For Goods Bought by Miss Eliza Roane from Parke Street (Box-folder 6:17)
    - 1824 July - October Invoice - For Goods Bought by Miss Eliza Roane from E.E.C. Manley (Box-folder 6:18)
    - 1824 - 1825 Invoice - For Goods Brought by Miss Eliza Roane from B.N. Dabney & Co. (Box-folder 6:19)
    - 1824 A Bill to the Alabama Congress (Box-folder 6:20)
    - 1825 May 4 Invoice - For Goods Bought by Albert G. Ruffin from Hall Neilson (Box-folder 6:21)
    - 1825 September 3-6 2 Receipts - For Goods Bought by Eliza Ruffin from H & R Kyle (Box-folder 6:22)
    - 1825 September 21 Some Records Pertaining to the Estate of William Ruffin, [3 items] (Box-folder 6:23)
    - 1825 - 1826 Albert G. Ruffin's Records (Box-folder 6:24)
    - 1826 April Jefferson Lottery Ticket (Box-folder 6:25)
    - 1826 - 1827 Invoice - For Goods Bought by Albert G. Ruffin from B.N. Dabney (Box-folder 6:26)
    - 1826 - 1827 6 Financial Items of Albert G. Ruffin (Box-folder 6:27)
    - 1826 - 1829 Mr. Eliza Ruffin's Accounts with Dr. G.A. Spiller (Box-folder 6:28)
    - 1826 - 1835 Albert G. Ruffin's Account Book (Box-folder 6:29)
    - 1827 October 24 Petition to the Hon. Andrew Stevenson for an Address that day after dinner to indicate his sentiments in relation to the upcoming Presidential election (Box-folder 6:30)
    - 1828 February 25 Bill of Exchange (Box-folder 6:31)
    - 1828 May-1829 June Invoice - For Goods Purchased by Mrs. A.G. Ruffin from Hall and Moore (Box-folder 6:32)
    - 1828 August - July Albert G. Ruffin in Account with Judith Nelson (Box-folder 6:33)
    - 1828 November 29 Bill of Lading - For Goods Shipped to Albert G. Ruffin (Box-folder 6:34)
    - 1829 March 7 Deposit Slip of Thomas Jefferson Randolph (Box-folder 6:35)
    - 1829 March Thomas Jefferson Randolph's Appointment of Bernard Peyton as Power of Attorney (Box-folder 6:36)
    - 1829 July 23 Inventory of Estate of Albert G. Ruffin (Box-folder 6:37)
    - 1829 - 1833 Mrs. Eliza Ruffin's Account with William Davenport (Box-folder 6:38)
    - 1829 - 1836 James M. Kildoe to Mrs. Eliza Ruffin with her Bill of Account (Box-folder 6:39)
    - 1830 Jan-Apr Mrs. Eliza Ruffin's Account with Thomas H. Drew (Box-folder 6:40)
    - 1830 February 11 Concerning a Business Transaction Signed by Peter Miner, J.H. Earnest and Eliza Anderson (Box-folder 6:41)
    - 1830 April-1832 Mrs. Eliza Ruffin's Account with John M. Anderson (Box-folder 6:42)
    - 1830 June -1832 Mrs. Eliza Ruffin's Account with I.H. Drew (Box-folder 6:43)
    - 1830 August-1831 Mrs. Eliza Ruffin's Account with Hall and Moore (Box-folder 6:44)
    - 1830 - 1832 Francis G. Ruffin's Account Book and Financial Papers (Box-folder 6:45)
    - 1831 March-1832 Mrs. Eliza Ruffin's Account with Dr. Street (Box-folder 6:46)
    - 1831 November Mrs. Eliza Ruffin in Account with Penitentiary Store (Box-folder 6:47)
    - 1831 Thomas Jefferson Randolph in Account with Sam Leitch (Box-folder 6:48)
    - 1832 October 8 Mrs. Eliza Ruffin in Account with John S. Sydnor (Box-folder 6:49)
    - 1833 Mrs. Eliza Ruffin's Account with Dr. Street, M.D (Box-folder 6:50)
    - 1834 March-Dec Mrs. Eliza Ruffin in Account with Thomas Talley (Box-folder 6:51)
    - 1834 June-Dec Mrs. Eliza Ruffin's Account with Dr. Street (Box-folder 6:52)
    - 1835 January - July Mrs. Eliza Ruffin's Account with Binford, Brooks, Gay & Co. (Box-folder 6:53)
    - 1835 May 6 A List of Voters on the Roll of Thomas Jefferson Randolph Objected to by Thomas W. Gilmer (Box-folder 6:54)
    - 1836 February 16 Receipt - For Goods Purchased by Eliza Ruffin from Binford, Brooks, Gay & Co. (Box-folder 6:55)
    - 1836 August - 1837 Mrs. Eliza Ruffin in Account with Binford, Brooks, Gay & Co. (Box-folder 6:56)
    - [c. 1836?] Epitaph of Martha Jefferson (Box-folder 6:57)
    - 1842 January 5 Thomas Jefferson Randolph in Account with Womble and Dean (Box-folder 6:58)
    - 1844 May 25 Receipt for thirty-eight pair of shoes bought by Thomas Jefferson Randolph and delivered by John, a servant of John O. Harris, for one dollar and twenty-five cents each (Box-folder 6:59)
    - 1864 December General Randolph in Account with C. Ancill (Box-folder 6:60)
    - 1864 15 Receipts - Quartermaster's Department, Confederate States of America, Thomas Jefferson Randolph - Quartermaster (Box-folder 6:61)
    - [ca. 1871] Reminiscences of Jane Hollins Nicholas Randolph (1798-1871) by Thomas Jefferson Randolph for their daughter, Eliza MacDonald Ruffin (Box-folder 6:62)
    - n.d. Fragment of a Bookplate (Box-folder 6:63)
    - n.d. [Nicholas P. Trist's List of Some Letters for the Randolph Book on Jefferson?] (Box-folder 6:64)
    - n.d. 6 Items of Records Pertaining to Estate of Albert G. Ruffin (Box-folder 6:65)
    - n.d. Personal Expense Account of [Thomas Jefferson Randolph] (Box-folder 6:66)
    - n.d. Describing the Duties of the Secretary of the Commonwealth (Box-folder 6:67)
    - n.d. Petition to the General Assembly for Educating Slaves before Freeing Them (Box-folder 6:68)
    - n.d. Mr. H. Wood in Account with Robert Rives and Co. (Box-folder 6:69)
    - n.d. Sale Book (Box-folder 6:70)
    - n.d. Coin Impressions (Virginia 150 cent piece) (Box-folder 6:71)
    - n.d. Notes on the Importance of Agriculture (Box-folder 6:72)
    - n.d. An Account of Slave [Sales?] (Box-folder 6:73)
    - n.d. "Notes of the Courses [ _ ] of Fields Cultivated by Isaiah Haden on Land Belonging to Wm. Short Esq." Perhaps owned by T. Jefferson (Box-folder 6:74)
    - n.d. Photostatic copy of "A Plan of the Ways Leading to Albemarle Courthouse" with negatives; for original see (OS Edgehill-Randolph Folder) (Box-folder 6:75)
    - n.d. Accounts of Colonel Nicholas (Box-folder 6:76)
    - n.d. Greeting Cards - [Twentieth Century?] (2 items) (Box-folder 6:77)
- Series III: Drawings, Surveys, etc.
  - [1794-1796?] Several drawings or plans of stands or tables (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - [ca. 1785], n.d. 3 Pieces of Paper believed owned by Thomas Jefferson, one piece designated "Virginia Paper" and one with a watermark (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - 1811 April 17 Thomas Jefferson Survey Map of Line Between "Lego" and "Pantops" (FC-2801, N-548), (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - 1813 September Map of Tomahawk Creek Lands, by Joseph Slaughter, endorsed by Thomas Jefferson (FC-2849) (Negative 35-138-A), (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - 1825 July 27 Plat of 1,699 acres of the Edgehill Tract surveyed by A. Broadhead (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - n.d. Survey and Plat of Land in Bedford County, Virginia (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - n.d. Thomas Jefferson Endorsed Wrapper (only) for "Surveys of Shadwell" (FC-3163), (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - n.d. Thomas Jefferson Endorsed Wrapper (only) for "Surveys of Lego" (FC-3164), (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - n.d. Plan for a well winch (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - n.d. Drawing of some type of unidentified mechanical equipment, labeled only "No. 4" (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - n.d. Thomas Jefferson Map of Area from Charlottesville to Milton (FC-3131, N-557), (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - n.d. Thomas Jefferson Map and Survey of Shadwell, Pantops, Lego, and Edgehill, roads from Charlottesville to various points in the area of Milton (N-526-A), (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - n.d. Thomas Jefferson Map and Survey of Shadwell, Pantops, Lego, and Edgehill, with springs and creek branches noted (FC-3137, N-526-C), (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - n.d. Thomas Jefferson Map and Survey of [Monticello?] (FC-3136, N-526-D), (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - n.d. Thomas Jefferson Map and Survey of Shadwell, Pantops, Lego, and Edgehill (FC-3138, N-526-E), (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - n.d. Thomas Jefferson Map and Survey of ["Shadwell"] with the notation "gate" (FC-3142, N-526-F), (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - n.d. Thomas Jefferson Survey Map of "Albemarle Lands" with note "measure of the triangles beginning them at S.W. end" (FC-3143, N-526-G), (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - n.d. Survey [possibly the East Range of the University of Virginia, with 3 Hotels?], (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - n.d. Survey [possibly the West Range of the University of Virginia, with 3 Hotels and Anatomical Hall ?], (OS Edgehill-Randolph Box)
  - n.d. "A Plan of the ways leading to Albemarle Courthouse ordered by the Honorable General Court to be taken under the direction of Messrs. James Quarles, James Garland, and William Woods, by Dan Smith (Negative 35-138-C), (OS Edgehill-Randolph Folder)
  - n.d. Chart of a High Water Mark of a River (OS Edgehill-Randolph Folder)
    Sabrina Rissing and Dan Weiss Sharon Defibaugh